Okay, בוקר טוב *boker tov*, it's good to be back. Today's דף
daf *daf* is כ"ה *chaf hey*, but we pick up on the...
on כ"ד עמוד ב' *chaf daled amud bet*, we're in a new
פרק *perek* about אין מקדישין *ein makdishin*. As you might have got
a sense, this... this מסכת *masechet* is not limited to ערכין *arachin*,
it really focuses on the last half of בחוקותי Bechukotai, *bechukotai* and
it deals with a range of things. So it starts with ערך
erech *erech*, but now we're into the second part of that where
it's when you're מקדיש makdish *makdish* a שדה Sadeh, *sadeh*, and it's
a period of the יובל Yovel *yovel*, how's that redeemed, you know,
what happens when the יובל Yovel. *yovel* comes and so on. And
actually the very end of בחוקותי *bechukotai* is תמורה *tmura*, which is
the next מסכת *masechet*. So just to understand, this is not like
a digression, it just really means stepping back and, you know, and
understanding what the whole topic of this, of this מסכת *masechet* is,
is it's really the range of different הקדשות *hakdashot* that about different
types of donations to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *beit hamikdash* that
are essentially focused on at the end of פרשת *parshat* בחוקותי *bechukotai*.
Done, done מסכת *masechet* by its name.
Well, correct. I mean the real names come from the, you, well,
depend actually, often from the first word. Anyway, different things. Okay, moving
on.
So picking up though on the bottom of כ"ד עמוד ב' *chaf
daled amud bet*, we are about three-fifths down, little ה' *hey* in
the, in the half brackets, הא מני רבנן Rabbanan, היא *ha mani
rabanan hi*. So let's actually go back and answer and just re-read
what the question is. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah *mishna* had said
that you, that you can't be מקדיש makdish. *makdish* a שדה sadeh
*sadeh* within two years of the יובל Yovel *yovel* because the תורה
Torah *torah* says על פי השנים הנותרות al pi hashanim hanotarot. *al
pi hashanim hanotarot*, based on the remaining years. But the גמרא Gemara
*gemara* based on another ברייתא braita *braita* or whatever revised that, or
רב Rav *rav* and שמואל Shmuel, *shmuel* revised that to say it
doesn't mean you can't be מקדיש makdish *makdish* at all, it means
it would be a very, it would be a very unwise to
be מקדיש makdish *makdish* because the idea that you do it based
on the remaining years is basically fifty שקל shekel *shekel* based on
בית זרע שעורים *beizera soreim*, חומר chomer שעורים *chomer seorim*, which we'll
talk about in the next משנה Mishnah *mishna*, and then that gets
divided by forty-nine years and you do it proportional to the amount
of years that are remaining. But that's only until the last two
years. That's גירוע *girua*. But when you have less than two years
left, then you don't do this גירוע *girua* and you do the
straight flat fifty שקל shekel *shekel*. And therefore what the משנה Mishnah.
*mishna* means is not that it doesn't work, but that it would
not be wise to do it. So that's one position of רב
Rav, *rav* and שמואל Shmuel *shmuel*. And then you have another debate
of רב Rav, *rav* and שמואל Shmuel *shmuel*, and that's an agreement,
then you have a debate of רב Rav *rav* and שמואל Shmuel
*shmuel*, what happens if somebody is מקדיש makdish. *makdish* a שדה *sadeh*
during the יובל Yovel, *yovel* itself. So if you're מקדיש makdish *makdish*
a שדה *sadeh* during the יובל Yovel *yovel* itself, then according to
שמואל Shmuel *shmuel* it's not קדוש kadosh *kadosh*, and according to רב
Rav *rav* it's קדוש kadosh. *kadosh* and you pay the full freight,
you pay the fifty שקל shekel *shekel*. Okay, so let's take a
look now at where the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is about this.
I'm going to actually start if it's okay just so we have
the flow from מיתיבי *meitvei*. So not where I said, it's about
ten lines up, but we'll do it quickly. So about, about, about
three lines, four lines under the little ג' *gimmel* at the beginning
of a line in the brackets, about ten lines from the top.
מיתיבי *meitvei*. מקדישין בין לפני יובל Yovel בין אחר יובל achar Yovel
*makdishin bein lifnei yovel bein achar yovel*. We have a ברייתא braita,
*braita* that says you can sanctify a field whether before the יובל
Yovel *yovel* begins or after the יובל Yovel *yovel* or after the
יובל Yovel *yovel*, ובשעת היובל עצמו לא יקדיש *ubesha'at hayovel atzmo lo
yakdish*, and the יובל Yovel *yovel* year itself you shall not sanctify,
ואם הקדיש אינה קדושה kedusha *ve'im hikdish eini kedusha*, and if you
sanctified it's not קדוש *kadosh*. It seems to be a straight ruling
like שמואל Shmuel *shmuel*, that if you sanctify on the יובל Yovel
*yovel*, the same way the יובל Yovel *yovel* causes the it to
go to the כהנים kohanim. *kohanim* and causes, you know, the change,
so if you try to do it on the יובל Yovel *yovel*
itself, it doesn't work at all. What does רב Rav? *rav* do
who says it works and it's a full fifty שקל shekel *shekel*?
So אמר לך רב *amar lecha rav*, so אינה קדושה kedusha *eini
kedusha*. So אמר לך רב *amar lecha rav*, רב *rav* will tell
you, אינה קדושה kedusha, בגירוע *eini kedusha begirua*, אבל קדוש ונותן חמישים
*aval kadosh venoten chamishim*. Oh, it means that you don't do the,
you don't deduct the amount it based on the amount of years
left because it's actually at the beginning of a cycle, like the
יובל Yovel *yovel* is the end of one cycle, beginning of next.
So you don't deduct it based on the amount of years left,
but you pay the full freight. That's what it really means. So
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says one minute, מכלל דלפני היובל *mikhlal de'lifnei
hayovel*, if that's what it means when it says it's not קדוש
*kadosh*, it really means it really means you don't do the deduction.
If that's really what it means, מכלל דלפני היובל *mikhlal de'lifnei hayovel*,
so the beginning of the ברייתא braita *braita* which says that it
is קדוש *kadosh* means you do a deduction. Means קדושה לגאול בגירוע
*kedusha lega'al begirua*, means that when it's before the יובל Yovel *yovel*
it's קדוש *kadosh* and you do the deduction. But you can't say
that because when it's within two years everybody agrees that you don't
do the deduction. והא רב ושמואל Rav and Shmuel דאמרי תרוייהו *veha
rav ushmuel de'amri tavaihu*, thank you, אין מקדישין לגאול בגירוע פחות משתי
שנים *ein makdishin lega'al begirua pachat mishtei shanim*, everybody agrees that you
don't do the deduction, so we're back to the question, which is
the משנה Mishnah, *mishna* says if you sanctify it on the יובל
Yovel *yovel* it's not קדוש *kadosh*, and רב *rav* says it is
קדוש *kadosh*. What are we going to do with that ברייתא Baraita,
*braita*? So אמר לך רב *amar lecha rav*, so רב *rav* says,
and here's where you left off yesterday, הא מני רבנן Rabbanan היא
*ha mani rabanan hi*, this is the rabbis, which rabbis we'll see
in a minute, ואנא דאמרי כרבי *va'ana de'amri kirebbi*, and I say
like רבי Rebbi. *rebbi*, דאמר ראשון ראשון בכלל שביעי שביעי בכלל *de'amar
rishon rishon bikhlal shevi'i shevi'i bikhlal*. So you learned this about a
week ago in the מסכת *masechet*, there's a general principle of רבי
Rebbi's *rebbi* that says that when the תורה Torah *torah* says from
this to that, does it mean inclusive of the endpoints or exclusive
of the endpoints, right? When it says that you cannot eat חמץ
*chametz* מיום הראשון עד יום השביעי *miyom harishon ad yom hashvi'i*, does
it mean including days one and seven? Yeah. Or does it mean
between days one and seven? But רבי Rebbi. *rebbi* says... From there
we learn a general principle that when it says until, it means
until and including. So therefore רב says look, רב says how do
I know, and this you said yesterday, how do I know that
it's קדוש on the יובל Yovel itself? Because the פסוק pasuk said,
ואם משנת היובל, ve'im mishnat haYovel, if you sanctify your field from
the year of the יובל. Yovel So that means, says רב, including
from and including, including the endpoint. So the sanctity works on the
יובל Yovel year itself. Fine. Who's that going like? Which hermeneutic principle
is that, that when you say from and until you include the
endpoints? That's רבי. Rebbi. So I am following רבי's Rebbi hermeneutic principle.
You're right, this ברייתא braisa says it's not only on the יובל,
Yovel, the יובל Yovel prevents the קדושה from taking effect. Fine, that's
a different hermeneutic principle, that's not רבי. Rebbi, But I'm saying like
רבי. Rebbi, So רבי Rebbi, says ראשון ראשון בכלל שביעי ושביעי בכלל,
rishon rishon bikhlal shvi'i veshvi'i bikhlal, one through seven means including one
and seven. הכא נמי, hacha nami, it should be משנת היובל, mishnat
haYovel, from the יובל Yovel year, ושנת היובל בכלל, ushnat haYovel bikhlal,
including the יובל Yovel year. Okay, fine. So you're right, what I'm
saying is not everybody, what I'm saying is רבי, Rebbi but nevertheless,
I don't have to work with that ברייתא, that ברייתא was a
different approach, but I still say that on the יובל Yovel year
itself it is קדוש. And now the גמרא Gemara gets into an
interesting question about this. That if it includes the יובל Yovel, year
itself, so think about it. You can therefore sanctify fields from the
יובל Yovel year until the next יובל Yovel year. Now, there's that
after the יובל Yovel year we normally assume that the counting starts
one through forty-nine and then you hit the יובל Yovel year. So
last, when if I'm sanctifying it on the יובל Yovel year itself,
that was last cycle's fifty, right? And then I have another one
through forty-nine and then the fields will revert. So how many total
years is there that my sanctity can be effective if I sanctify
it on the יובל Yovel year itself? Fifty, right? The יובל Yovel
year itself and then the next forty-nine. So if we have to
do a reduce it according to the number of remaining years or
a proportional division or whatever, then we should take the fifty שקל
shekel and divide fifty by fifty because the sanctity process can begin
at the יובל Yovel year and that's one and then has forty-nine
years left. So therefore the fifty, if we want to divide per
year, should be one שקל shekel, per year. We normally assume you
have forty-nine years in which the קדושה can stretch and therefore you
divide fifty by forty-nine and you get one and a פונדיון. pundyon.
So that's going to now be our question. According to you רב,
that the process can start at the יובל Yovel year itself, then
there's a fifty years, then it should work out to be a
שקל shekel, a year and not a שקל shekel, and a little
bit. So let's take a look.
So
the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, playing the role of Michael today will be Dov Weinstein. He
already asked this question when I prepared. I see. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
ושל רבי, veshel Rebbi, one minute, if it's like רבי, Rebbi meaning
forget it, if it's like רבי, Rebbi I mean what I mean
is like if that's true that you really start in the יובל
Yovel year itself, פונדיון מאי עבידתיה? pundyon mai avidteih?
Why is it one שקל Shekel and a פונדיון pundyon per year?
Right? One and a little bit, which means you're doing a divide
by forty-nine. It should be exactly one שקל, Shekel, it should be
a divide by fifty. וכי תימא לית ליה, vechi teima leit leih,
maybe רבי Rebbi
maybe רבי Rebbi would actually say it's not one and a bit,
maybe he would say it's exactly one. Maybe אינה הכי נמי. eina
hachi nami. But then you can't say that because the משנה Mishnah.
we're about to read on the next דף says, הקדיש שתים ושלש
שנים לפני היובל, hikdish shtayim veshalosh shanim lifnei haYovel, let's say it
was two or three years before the יובל, Yovel how do you
do the math? רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, אומר אני, omer ani, I
say, נותן סלע ופונדיון, noten sela upundyon, you figure a סלע sela
and a פונדיון pundyon per year. So you're saying you're going like
רבי Rabbi in order to count to begin on the יובל Yovel
year, but רבי Rabbi himself says it's a divide by forty-nine. And
according to you it should be a divide by fifty. So how
do you do this? So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי כרבי יהודה
סבירא ליה. Rebbi keRebbi Yehuda sevira leih. Oh,
just like Dov said. רבי Rabbi, holds like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda,
דאמר בשנת חמשים עולה לכאן ולכאן, de'amar bishnat chamishim ola lechan ulechan,
that the יובל Yovel year itself is not year just year fifty
of the past, it's year one of the next cycle. So if
the יובל Yovel year itself is year one of the next cycle,
then even if you go from the beginning of the יובל Yovel
to the next יובל, Yovel you only have forty-nine years because the
יובל Yovel year is one and the next year is two and
so on, so there's only forty-nine. Actually there's a nice, you know,
correspondence conceptually with that, although the גמרא Gemara has never said that,
you know, but but if you consider the יובל Yovel to also
be one of the next cycle, there's a there's an intuitive reason
why you would want to also assume that some of the laws
of the following years can apply during the יובל Yovel? itself because
conceptually it's not just a יובל Yovel, year, it's also the beginning
of the next cycle. So the fact that it says you could
be מקדיש makdish it like you can after the יובל Yovel? works
nicely together with the idea that the יובל Yovel year is also
the beginning of the next cycle.
That's what it says all the time, שנת החמשים שנה זו וזו,
shnat hachamishim shana zu vezu, it doesn't really sneak it in as
like, you know, year fifty and year one too.
I understand. So okay, I you know, I think that this debate
is more fleshed out in like in if I remember correctly in
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and other places. So... Or get there we
can discuss it, but for now we'll just accept that that's the
position.
Okay, and it seems more intuitive that if you're dividing by fifty,
and there's a fifty-year cycle, that's also true.
Then if the תורה Torah gave you, if the תורה Torah said
fifty שקל, Shekel to do it according to the years, that there
was a reason to think that there would be a divide by
fifty going on here. That is also true. Okay, let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, now לשמואל, l'Shmuel, לימא רבי כרבנן סבירא ליה. leima Rabbi k'Rabbanan
svira lei. Now according to שמואל, Shmuel. we should say, it would
make sense that רבי Rabbi. goes like the רבנן, Rabbanan that says
that basically it's,
we, wait a minute, the רבנן Rabbis that would say, oh yeah,
that the fifty years, that the fifty year does not count מכאן
ומכאן. mikan u'mikan. Why? דאי כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, D'ee k'Rabbi Yehuda
svira lei, if רבי Rabbi would hold like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
then סלע ושתי פונדיוס מיבעי ליה. sela u'shtei pundyos mibayei lei. It
would have to be a סלע sela and two פונדיוס. pundyos. What
does this mean? It means like this, that it's possible if you
combine
שמואל Shmuel with the רבנן's position, you're going to get to only
be forty-eight years you could be מקדיש. makdish Because according to שמואל
you can't be מקדיש makdish on the יובל Yovel. year itself, right?
And if the יובל Yovel, year starts as year one like רבי,
Rabbi so you can't be מקדיש makdish on year one, you're only
left with forty-eight years you could be מקדיש. makdish So it would
become a divide by forty-eight. So fifty divided by forty-eight would be
one and two פונדיון, pundyon, because two פונדיון pundyon is basically, you
know, a forty-eighth or something. So therefore we now you can't really
combine the position of שמואל that you can't be מקדיש makdish on
the יובל Yovel year with the position that of you go basic
with the position that you start counting only that
you can't be מקדיש makdish on the יובל Yovel. year with the
position that the יובל Yovel. year counts as year one. If you
did, I mean you could combine it, but then you would have
a position of one and two coins, one and two פונדיון, pundyon,
and it's not the position of רבי. Rabbi רבי Rabbi, we know
in the next משנה Mishnah is one and one coin. So the
גמרא Gemara says you're right. על כרחך דשמואל, Al karchach d'Shmuel, you
must say according to שמואל that says you can't be מקדיש makdish
on the יובל Yovel? year, that there have to be according to
רבי forty-nine years that come after. So therefore you must say רבי
כרבנן סבירא ליה. Rabbi k'Rabbanan svira lei. רבי holds like the רבנן
that the יובל Yovel. year does not count as year one. Okay,
so basically what we're saying is the point that assuming certainly רבי,
but let's say assuming everybody holds that the division that you it's
a divide by forty-nine, how do you get divide by forty-nine? So
according to רב that you can be מקדיש makdish in the יובל
Yovel year, you have to say that the יובל Yovel, year is
year one, so you get a divide by forty-nine. According to שמואל
that says you can't be מקדיש makdish in the יובל Yovel year,
you have to say that the יובל Yovel, year is zero, doesn't
count as year one and year one counts later in order to
get a divide by forty-nine. But in theory, based on the way
you would combine the positions, you could get a divide by fifty
and you could get a divide by forty-eight. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear. ולא גואלין אחר היובל פחות משנה. V'lo goalin achar haYovel pachot
mishana. You cannot redeem after the יובל Yovel. less than a year.
Now what does that mean? Why can't it sounds like if I
was מקדיש makdish it on year one, I have to wait a
year before redeeming it. But that's not true, never heard of such
a thing. So what does that line even mean that you can't
be מקדיש makdish less than a year after יובל? Yovel. So now
we're going to have two very different interpretations based on רב and
שמואל.
בשלמא, B'shlama, you can't redeem it.
Thank you, you can't redeem. But we also never heard that. Right,
why not? I sanctified it, I redeem it right away. Right, sounds
like in the תורה Torah, you could redeem it as soon as
you sanctified it, right? From the very beginning of the fifty years.
So what does this mean you can't redeem it right after the
יובל, Yovel, in the year after the יובל? Yovel. So בשלמא לשמואל,
b'shlama l'Shmuel, according to שמואל it works. ולא גואלין אחר היובל פחות
משנה. Lo goalin achar Yovel pachot mishana. What it means is that
from the time the יובל Yovel begins, you cannot redeem it for
a year because you really can't sanctify it for a year. So
it's not so much you can't redeem it, but really what it's
a funny way of saying you can't sanctify during the year of
the יובל. Yovel, This whole process of sanctifying and redeeming does not
begin for a year from the beginning of the יובל, Yovel as
a way of saying it does not begin until after the יובל
Yovel, year. All right, so it should work. It's a little funny
way of saying it, but it could work. אלא לרב, Ella l'Rav,
מאי אחר יובל שנה? mai achar Yovel shana? What does it mean
for a year you can't redeem it? That doesn't make any sense.
When could you not redeem it according to רב? So the גמרא
Gemara says no. מי סבר אחר יובל ממש? Mi savar achar Yovel
mamash? It doesn't mean immediately after the יובל. Yovel It doesn't mean
year one or after the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah or יום כיפור
Yom Kippur of the יובל. Yovel מאי אחר יובל? Mai achar Yovel?
What does it mean after the יובל? Yovel Top of כ"ה עמוד
א'. chaf-hey amud aleph. באמצע יובל. B'emtza Yovel. It just means in
a normal case. I sanctified a field on year twenty-three, it doesn't
matter. So what and when it says אין מקדישין לאחר היובל פחות
משנה, ein makdishin l'achar haYovel pachot mishana, it doesn't mean a year
with less than a year after the יובל. Yovel. It means if
you're being מקדיש makdish it sometime not on the יובל yovel itself,
sometime in the middle of a cycle, that's all אחר יובל yovel
means. If you're מקדיש makdish it sometime in the middle cycle, you
can't be פודה podeh less than a year. What does it mean
you can't be פודה podeh less than a year? When I figure
out the number of remaining years, I have to do it in
whole units. I can't say there's two and three-quarters years and I'll
redeem based on two and three-quarters years. No, you can't redeem in
a unit less than a year. That's all it means. Don't get
confused with the אחר היובל, achar haYovel, it just means don't redeem
in units less than a year. Okay, so here's what it means.
דכל כמה דלא מליא לשנה, dechol kamma delo malya lishana, if the
year isn't full, לא מיגרע ליה. lo migra lei. You cannot deduct
it. Meaning, if I have two and three quarters years left until
the יובל, yovel right, how many years do I figure that out?
So one way of saying it because the language is really you
deduct. You take 50 and you subtract the years that have gone
away. So I cannot subtract
47 and a
quarter. Okay, since that the the the year that's passed since the
last יובל yovel is
46 and three quarters. Since the year that's passed since the last
יובל, yovel the number of years is I only count the number
of full years that's passed since last יובל. yovel So if I'm
two and three quarters left, I can't say oh there's also been
an extra quarter year that's passed, I'll deduct that extra quarter year.
No, it hasn't been a full year you can't deduct it. An
easier way to say it is when you're counting the number of
years that remain, you round up. So if I have two and
three quarters years remain, I have to round up to three. You
only do full units and you round up. You cannot you cannot
you need a full year in order to count in order to
deduct it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן, mai
kamashma lan, what is this teaching me? שאין מחשבין חדשים עם ההקדש
she'ein mechashevin chodashim im hahekdesh that you don't sort of with הקדש,
hekdesh, you know, sort of count number of months in order for
in order you know for your benefit, right? If you round up
the number of years remaining, that הקדש hekdesh gets a better deal.
So the basic point is is that you don't do you know
it's only full years, it's not months and you cannot do months
in order to take in order to hurt הקדש. hekdesh. So the
גמרא Gemara, says הא בהדיא קתני, ha behedya katani, that's מפורש meforash
in the משנה. Mishnah, שאין מחשבין חדשים עם ההקדש. she'ein mechashevin chodashim
im hahekdesh. You cannot do months with הקדש. hekdesh. It's full years
towards הקדש's hekdesh benefit. So the גמרא Gemara says yeah it all
means the same thing. מה טעם קאמר. ma ta'am ka'amar. It's explaining
it. מה טעם לא גאול לאחר יובל פחות משנה? ma ta'am lo
ga'ul le'achar yovel pachot mishana? Why can you not do units less
than a year? משום דאין מחשבין חדשים עם ההקדש mishum de'ein mechashevin
chodashim im hahekdesh because when it comes you don't figure out number
of months with הקדש. hekdesh. You figure out number of years. Okay,
so you only use year units, but only use year units to
הקדש's hekdesh benefit. Meaning that when we're figuring out the number of
years that remain, you round up. When you're figuring out the number
of years that have gone, you round down. Okay, so you only
do year units but towards הקדש's hekdesh benefit. You round up when
you figure out the number of years remain. Okay, good. That's how
רב ושמואל Rav and Shmuel, explained that line. Now we're moving beyond
רב ושמואל, Rav and Shmuel finishing up the משנה, mishna. about seven
lines from the top, כ"ה עמוד א'. kaf hey amud aleph. אין
מחשבין חדשים. ein mechashevin chodashim.
Like we just said, you don't figure out months, you know, you
don't you only do whole year units. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. מנין
שאין מחשבין חדשים עם ההקדש? minayin she'ein mechashevin chodashim im hahekdesh? How
do I know that you only keep it at the units of
years and not months? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar וחישב לו הכהן את
כסף vechishev lo hakohen et kesef על פי השנים al pi hashanim,
הנותרות.
You figure out the amount you owe based on the remaining years.
And it says על פי השנים, שנים אתה מחשב ואי אתה מחשב
חדשים. shanim ata mechashev ve'ei ata mechashev chodashim. You do it by
year units, not months units. And again, towards הקדש's hekdesh benefit, so
you round up based on the number of years remaining. מנין שאם
אתה רוצה לעשות חדשים לשנה עושה? minayin she'im ata rotze la'asot chodashim
leshana ose?
How do I know that if you want to do months towards
a year you can? Now, what would that mean? Meaning, let's say
it's in הקדש's hekdesh benefit to round down rather than round up.
What's the case that it's in הקדש's hekdesh benefit to round down
based on the remaining of years? היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the
case? כגון דאקדשה בפלגא דארבעין ותמני. kegon de'akdesha bepalga de'arba'in vetamnei.
Let's say it is 48 and a half. Okay, now, meaning that
there's a year and a half left towards towards the יובל. yovel,
Now you remember what's the הלכה? halacha? If you sanctify it within
two years of the יובל, yovel, you pay full freight, right? So
if I now I have a year and a half left to
יובל. yovel Where am I at? If I have to do whole
year units. If you round up, then there's two years left. Oh,
phew, I can still do the the deduction. But if you right
so if you round down, there's only one year left and I
have to pay the full amount. So here it's in הקדש's hekdesh
benefit to have you round down rather than round up. So how
do you know you can do that? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar וחישב
לו הכהן vechishev lo hakohen מכל מקום. mikol makom. The verse that
the כהן Kohen will figure it for you, do you need a
napkin here? Okay. It means regard gives an extra sort of an
extra latitude, so if it's towards הקדש's hekdesh benefit, they can choose
to have it round down rather than round up. וחישב לו,
vechishev
lo, meaning whatever is to his benefit.
I know. Okay. Anyway, so that's the basic rule which is that
within two years you go the full freight, you do it by
whole year units, you normally round you round up or round down
towards הקדש's hekdesh benefit, and the interesting debate of רב ושמואל which
is what if you're מקדיש makdish during the יובל yovel year itself.
Now let's go in terms of how you figure out what is
how much you actually pay. So the תורה Torah says here, yes.
It says here at the end of
בחוקותי, ואם משדה אחוזתו יקדיש איש להשם, ve’im misedei achuzato yakdish ish
laHashem, if
you sanctify a field of your inheritance, not a purchased field,
והיה ערכך לפי זרעו זרע חומר שעורים בחמישים שקל כסף, vehaya erkecha
lefi zaro zera chomer seorim bachamishim shekel kasef, 50 shekel. So that's
basically the amount of a field that you would plant this amount
of barley seed, 50 shekel for that acreage. אם משנת היובל יקדיש
שדהו, im mishnat hayovel yakdish sadehu, if you do it again from
the beginning of the יובל, yovel whether the year after the year
of the יובל Yovel. was what was debated, then כערכך יקום, ke’erkecha
yakum, the full amount, 50 shekel. ואם אחר היובל יקדיש שדהו, ve’im
achar hayovel yakdish sadehu, if it's after the beginning of the cycle,
וחישב לו הכהן את הכסף על פי השנים הנותרות, vechishev lo hakohen
et hakesef al pi hashanim hanotarot, you figure out the remaining years,
עד שנת היובל ad shnat hayovel until the יובל, Yovel ונגרע מערכך
venigra me’erkecha and you deduct appropriately. Okay, so that is what we're
focusing on now. So first we did when are you sanctifying it
during the cycle, and now we're going to do how much you
pay, 50 shekel for this field that can be planted with a
חומר chomer of barley seed. So let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishnah, המקדיש שדהו בשעת היובל, hamakdish sadehu bish’at hayovel,
if you sanctify your field, meaning when the יובל Yovel is in
practice. It's funny that it has to give that qualification because you
might as well just say that from the first משנה Mishnah. as
well, but okay. נותן בזרע חומר שעורים חמישים שקל כסף. noten bezera
chomer seorim chamishim shekel kasef.
Then for every, for this field which is again the planting of
the amount of barley seed, a חומר Chomer of barley seed, the
amount of field that's planted with that amount, 50 shekel for that
acreage. And then you make it proportional. If it's two and a
half of that acreage or a quarter of that acreage, everything is
proportional, but if it's the full 50 years, 49 years, it's 50
shekel for that acreage. Now, היו שם נקעים עמוקים עשרה טפחים. hayu
sham neka’im amukim asara tefachim. Let's say you have deep crevices that
are more than ten טפחים tefachim deep. A טפח tefach is about
three inches, or maybe, excuse me, yeah, about three inches, maybe a
little bit more, so anyway, three and a half inches, so figure
that's about three feet, okay? So you've got a crevice three feet
deep or deeper. או סלעים גבוהים עשרה טפחים, o sla’im gvohim asara
tefachim, or big rocks three feet or taller, אין נמדדים עמה, ein
nimdadim ima, they do not count towards the acreage because you can't
plant on a big rock or you can't plant in a deep
crevice. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask you also can't plant
on a small rock, but we'll get to that, okay? But anyway,
that's not part of the acreage. So what do you do with
the rocks and with the crevices? Well, first of all, when you
figure out the acreage, you reduce, you deduct from their area, and
in terms of, but you sanctify the whole field. So for those
you figure out how much would be the market value of those.
Those don't go according to the acreage of the תורה, Torah 50
shekel for this acreage, which is a fixed amount, like ערך for
people is a fixed amount. This would go because it doesn't fit
into that, it's not an area that's plantable, so what do I
do if I sanctify something that's not plantable? Let's say I just
sanctify a field that's all rocks. Let's say I sanctify a car.
So you go by market value. So for those areas you don't
count them towards this acreage and you do them separately based on
market value.
Does that mean things like a drought, nothing's going to be growing,
do you deduct anything?
No, no, no, it has to do with the nature of the
field.
So if the field like completely burns and is now parched and
you
can't do anything with it? That's an interesting question, but that's not
just a drought. You said a drought before, right? Yeah. I don't
know. I mean, that's a good question. I mean, I think that
there is some discussion about it if the ground is completely impenetrable
or something like that. So I have to check, but there is
definitely discussion about it. Okay, so now it says like this. So
that's if you had the full 50 years in front of you.
פחות מכאן אם אינן עשרה טפחים נמדדים עמה, pachot mikan im einan
asara tefachim nimdadim ima, if it's not ten טפחים tefachim higher or
deep, נמדדים עמה nimdadim ima they're counted with the field. הקדישה שתים
ושלש שנים לפני היובל. hikdisha shtayim veshalosh shanim lifnei hayovel. Now let's
say it wasn't 50 years to go, 49 years to go, there
were two or three years to go. We quoted this just a
minute ago. נותן סלע ופונדיון לשנה. noten sela upundiyon leshana. It's a
סלע sela and a פונדיון pundiyon for a year. A סלע sela
is a שקל, Shekel a פונדיון pundiyon is one forty-eighth. So 49
times one and one forty-eighth gets you 50 and a little bit.
So the little bit is just for the money changer. Anyway, so
you give a סלע sela and a bit per year. Okay, that's
so that's if there's less than the full 49 years. ואם אמר.
ve’im amar. Now let's say the guy says, do you have a
payment plan? הריני נותן דבר שנה בשנה. hareini noten davar shana beshana.
Can I give you, can we work out like a payment plan
that I will do it a little bit each year? Now it's
in the owner's interest to make sure that he redeems it before
the יובל Yovel hits because if he doesn't redeem it before the
יובל Yovel hits, right, what does the פסוק pasuk say? I'll read
it, that's the next משנה, Mishna, it says like this. It says
so, ואם לא יגאל את השדה ואם מכר את השדה לאיש אחר
לא יגאל עוד והיה השדה בצאתו ביובל קודש להשם כשדה החרם לכהן
תהיה אחוזתו. ve’im lo yigal et hasadeh ve’im machar et hasadeh le’ish
acher lo yiga’el od vehaya hasadeh betzeto bayovel kodesh laHashem kisdei hacherem
lakohen tihye achuzato.
It goes to the כהנים. kohanim, There'll be some debate about what
happens if it wasn't sold to somebody else. But anyway, so he
really has to try to buy it back before the יובל. Yovel
Let's say he can't get the money together, that amount of money.
So he says, well, let's work out a payment plan. I'll buy
it back now and I'll pay you off slowly. He would really
want to do that. Not allowed. You have to pay in full.
אין שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, you don't listen to him. אלא
נותן את כולו, ela noten et kulo, you have to pay the
full amount if you want to redeem it, כאחד, ke’echad, in one
unit. Now, אחד הבעלים ואחד כל אדם. echad habalim ve’echad kol adam.
Now anybody can redeem it, not only the owner can redeem it,
anybody can redeem it. ומה בין בעלים לכל אדם. uma bein ba’alim
lechol adam. What's the difference whether the owner redeems it or somebody
else? In terms of, well first we'll discuss later what happens when
the יובל hits, but even before the יובל hits, what's the difference
when they want to redeem it? אלא שבעלים נותנין חומש וכל אדם
אין נותנין חומש. ella she'ba'alim notnin chomesh v'chol adam ein notnin chomesh.
The בעלים ba'alim have to add a fifth, a normal person does
not have to add a fifth. So you do the value, the
fixed fee per the 49 years, you figure it out based on
the acreage, and then if you're the owner and you're redeeming your
own field, then you actually have to add an extra. Sort of
like the opposite of pawn shops. Like doesn't a pawn shop work
that if you sell something, then you get a right to buy
it back at a little bit less than whatever? Anyway, this is
the opposite. You were מקדיש makdish it, if you want to buy
it back, if you're the guy who was מקדיש makdish wants to
buy it back,
you have to pay higher.
You have to pay extra to buy it back. And you have
to pay חומש. chomesh. Yeah, but if you don't buy it back
and the יובל hits, even if somebody else bought it back, you
lose it. So if, so it doesn't matter if your friend bought
it back and then gave it to you or whatever. We'll actually
talk about that. We'll talk about that. That's the next משנה. Mishnah,
If you're not the one to buy it back, if somebody else
bought it back, even if it winds up in your hands, once
the יובל hits, it goes to the כהנים, Kohanim. you're out. So
therefore you're really going to want to buy it back if you
want to keep it before the יובל hits and you directly.
I don't understand why I would want to engage in this whole
transaction.
Well, I don't know, why do people give and why do people
donate things to, to, to...
Just give the money.
Okay, but you felt so, such a sense of largesse and I
don't know what, something motivated you and you were מקדיש your field.
Why buy it back? Well, so I would, I thought the question
was going to be, why do we put up obstacles for buying
it back? Why do we make you pay more?
Is it really because, you know, the guy should have kept it
with the temple?
So that's what I think. I think the question, I think the
point is like this, is that if you were מקדיש it, then
what's the temple going to do with the field unless it starts
wanting to get into the agriculture business? They're going to want to
sell it. So they sell it to somebody else or they'll sell
it at the market, well this isn't market value, but whatever it
is, the fixed value. There's no reason for somebody else to pay
an additional, that's just the temple trying to, to liquidate this into
money. But you, you, you know, if you sell it and buy
it back, then it sort of undermines that whole initial act of
donation and largesse, right? Because it's not when you gave it, somehow
there is something more powerful about giving, about giving something that's yours,
that's your field, especially if it's אחוזה, achuza, you know, in a
certain sense than just taking out and writing a check. So at
least my understanding is that the reason there's somewhat of a fine,
if you will, or an extra amount, is because it a little
bit undermines the largesse if you're buying back your own thing. So
if you're going to buy it back, it's not just the market
value. You actually give something extra
to make it a more, if it's, if you're just translating it
into cash in terms of you and הקדש, hekdesh, then it should
be more. Okay, it loses the symbolic power so it should be
more. That's how I understand it.
So that's not when you're buying it back, that's not the ideal.
Well, I don't know if it's not the ideal, but then if
we don't want to undermine the initial act, that's at least my
סברא. sevara. Then we should do something more. The other point though
is that it might be the ideal because if you don't buy
it back, you're going to be out this field for, for life,
because then when the יובל hits, it's going to, it's going to
leave your inheritance. This is a field of inheritance. So you, so
you know, on the one hand, it's like as you said, it's
really stupid. Why would you be מקדיש this field that's your, you
know, inherited plot property to the בית המקדש, give them something else?
But on the other hand, if you did it, it's a really
powerful act, a religious act, right? But the point is that now
you really run the risk if you don't buy it back of
it, of it being lost, lost to your family completely. That's going
to be the consequence.
הקדש hekdesh doesn't want a field.
It doesn't want your field. It'll sell to somebody else. But if
you're the one that's going to buy it back, which you now
have a very powerful incentive, like you wake up the next day
and said, okay, that was like, that was like a wonderful, you
know, momentary act of, of largesse, but like what did I do?
I've vowed to disassociate this from my family inheritance, right? So you
have a real high, high motive to buy it back.
But you're not allowed to buy it back anymore after יובל, seems
like some point, it's some point it wants to keep the field.
I don't know if it's that.
Why would they take away your...
I think it again, the question is הקדש hekdesh thinking about them
as like, as a, as a, as a financial entity and they
want it sort of in their pockets or they want it to
invest in it or something, which is crazy, because why not just
liquidate it, translate it into cash and so on? I think it
has more to do with the concept of your donation and the
concept of יובל, which is, is that again, if you're staying in
that mode of I've given something to God and this thing that's
a very powerful thing, it's my, you know, my inherited plot of
land, and you're, you've kept in that mode, you haven't bought it
back, then the idea is, you know, then if יובל comes and
you get it back, again you haven't done that, but if you
give it and יובל comes and יובל sort of then re, you
know, makes it permanently owned by הקדש, hekdesh, but again, that's, though
on the one hand, it's a really big thing to do that.
And the consequence is that הקדש hekdesh will keep it because, but
not again, not because they're investing in it as a field, but
because of the significance of you fully taking something out of your
inheritance and giving it to God. Okay, but if you want to
reverse that because now a little bit of more, you know, pragmatic
sort of sense of oh my God, what have I done, then,
then you have to make, you know, make up for it and
give more. That's the way I read this whole thing. Okay.
All right, but I don't read it as like oh this is
because הקדש hekdesh now
wants... Okay, so that's
etcetera, says the גמרא, Gemara תנא, Tana, we taught in
a ברייתא, כור זרע ולא כור תבואה. Kor zera velo kor tevuah.
So it's a כור, Kor, which is the חומר is the same
as a כור, Kor, so the amount of grain is the grain
of seed, not the amount that will produce that amount of that
amount of grain, meaning if you take a, you know, I don't
know, a bag of barley seed, and the question is how big
of a field do you plant with the barley seed? Then there's
another question: how much of a field do you need to produce
that amount of barley seed? I certainly hope that the latter is
a lot smaller than the former, right? Because then you're going to
all this effort and you're only taking back everything that you produced.
So obviously a certain, you know, one seed you get a whole
stalk of barley which produces a lot of seed and there's a
multiplier effect. So the idea of the amount of this barley seed
is the size of a field that you would plant this barley
seed in, not that would produce this barley seed. Okay, so that's
ולא כור תבואה. Velo kor tevuah. מפולת יד ולא מפולת שוורים, Mapolet
yad velo mapolet shevarim, the amount that would be if you were
spreading the seed with a hand rather than by oxen. If oxen,
some people would put the bag of seed on an ox, make
a little hole in it, the ox would walk back and forth
and it would spread the seed. Apparently that comes out faster or
in greater density than when you spread it by your hand. So
if you're doing it by your hand, that's a larger size field.
Okay. The larger the field, by the way, the better you are,
means that you can be a very large field but the cost
is less to you, okay, so to redeem it. So these two
things
make it a larger field. תני לוי, Tani Levi, לוי Levi taught,
לא מעבה ולא מדק, Lo me'aveh velo medak, the seed is not
overly thick seed and not overly thin seed, אלא בינוני, Ela beinoni,
average size seed. Okay fine. By the way, what I think is
fascinating about this is you might have imagined that this, although conceptually
it was this, it really there was a clear sort of, you
know, known measure that was identified as that, right? You know, basically
like we say a foot. A foot doesn't mean get out your
foot and start measuring, right? The same like, you know, but you
know, maybe that was conceptually where it started, but then it gets
translated into a very quantifiable amount, a fixed measure. But from the
fact that the גמרא Gemara, has to describe like this and like
this and like this and not like that, you know, it sounds
like at least in the time of the גמרא Gemara they did
not have a concept of what is the fixed size and therefore
you would really have to like, you know, actually measure it in
practice. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: היו שם
נקיקים עמוקים, Hayu sham nekikim amukim, if there were these deep crevices
or big
stones, בלקדש בהן פי נפשייהו, Belikadesh bahen pi nafshaihu, so why aren't
they sanctified even if they're not part of the field, says the
גמרא, Gemara let them be sanctified based on the same principle of
a fifty, you know, a fifty שקל shekel, per for this size
etcetera. And if they're sanctified based on that same principle, then it
doesn't matter, right? If they all have the same measurement apply to
them, we might as well just count them in the same area,
right? Even if you consider them separate, if in the end the
proportion you're going to pay and the amount you're going to be
pay is based on the same system, we might as well just
consider it all as one. וכי תימא, Vechi teima, if you say,
כיון דלא הוי בית כור לא הוי קדשי, Keivan dela havei beit
kor la havei kadshi, no, maybe it needs to be a full
בית כור Beit kor or else the whole thing doesn't work, and
these are too small. So the גמרא Gemara, says, one minute, והתניא,
Vehatanya, but that's not true, it could be any proportion any size.
שדה, it says if you sanctify a field. מה תלמוד לומר? Ma
talmud lomar? לפי שנאמר זרע חומר שעורים בחמישים שקל כסף, Lefi shene'emar
zera chomer se'orim bachamishim shekel kesaf,
if it's a certain amount of barley for fifty שקל, אין לי
אלא שתיקן יין זה, Ein li ela shetikan yan ze, maybe that's
only if it's minimally that big. מנין לרבות לתך, Minayin lerabot letach,
how do I know about a לתך, Letach, which is less than
that amount, וחצי לתך סאה ותרקב וחצי תרקב, Vechatzi letach se'ah vetarkav
vechatzi tarkav,
how do I know even much smaller sizes? תלמוד לומר שדה מכל
מקום, Talmud lomar sadeh mikol makom, it says a field, it doesn't
matter what the size is. So it's proportional. The rate is fifty
שקל to this size, but whatever size it is, you do the
math. One minute, so therefore, if that's true, why is the rock
or the crevice treated differently? So אמר מר עוקבא בר חמא, Amar
Mar Ukva bar Chama, הכא בנקיקים מלאי מים, Hacha benekikim melei mayim,
we're talking about crevices that are filled with water, דלא בני זריעה
נינהו, Dela benei zeri'ah ninhu, you can't plant on them. So yes,
meaning if it were a certain type of crevice, depending on how
narrow or how wide, right, you could imagine that you could plant
in a crevice. But no, this is a deep narrow crevice or
filled with water, it's some type of crevice that can't be planted.
And since it can't be planted, it's not part of this math
because this math is זרע חומר שעורים, Zera chomer se'orim, a field
that is plantable. This is not plantable. The גמרא Gemara says, דיקא
נמי דקתני דומיא דסלעים, Deika nami dekatani dumya desla'im, that makes sense
because it's made parallel to rocks, and the issue with rocks is
that it can't be planted. שמע מינה, Shema mina, that's a good
point. So these are areas in the field that can't be planted
and therefore they do not get counted with the area of the
field, they get treated separately. The גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, Ei
hachi, if that's true, they don't count at all. Well, they're not,
no, well, the way רש״י Rashi says, although it's not clear in
the משנה, Mishnah, is that it's based on their market value. It's
not based on the fixed fifty שקל per, although that's not explicit
in the משנה. Mishnah Okay, but they are not counted as part
of the area of the field. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the
גמרא, Gemara פחות מכאן נמי, Pachas mikan nami, even if it's a
smaller rock or a smaller crevice, it's not plantable. plantable area. The
גמרא Gemara says, no. הנהו נגני דארעא מיקרו. Hanu niganay de'ara mikeru.
Those are called puddles of the ground—because remember we said it was
filled with water—or שידלי דארעא מיקרו. shidlay de'ara mikeru. It's called like
a backbone of the ground, meaning it's called like a bump, a
puddle, meaning at a certain size, you don't measure every millimeter and
ask, can this millimeter be planted? Right, you have a little bit
more of a macro view. So if it's a certain if it's
not too deep or not too high, then you view it as
part of the field even if this particular area cannot be planted,
and you still count it in the area. But if it's very
high, and עשרה טפחים asara tefachim is the standard by the way,
height and depth that we consider something to be a different domain.
So if it's very high or very deep, then it's not part
of the field. Of course, the interesting question is, fine, let's say
it's low, but let's say it takes up a large percentage of
the area. Right, let's say you have a low-lying rock or a
low-lying puddle that's fifty percent of the field. You know, that's a
different question. How what percentage of the field can you consider it
to be trivial and incorporated and the other not? So I don't
know if that's, you know, it's not discussed here. So if you
want an answer to that, I'll have to see if it is
discussed elsewhere. Yes.
Is there any minimum size for it to be considered a field?
Like, you know, like apparently not.
So you can just have like your little
well, I guess that's an interesting question. Let's say it's so tiny
that nobody would ever plant barley in it. Like it would be
a little garden patch or something like that, that it would be
absurd to be technically you could plant barley, but it would be
absurd to do that. All right, all good questions to which I
don't know the answer. I will try to research some of this
and get back to you. All right.
Yes. It's so removed, we're so removed from this agricultural system. I
mean, the value of bedrock plot in Manhattan is so far
above an arable plot in Manhattan.
Right, but we're not talking about cities, you know, we're talking about
what about in Kansas? What's the what's the value of that type
of stuff? Right, we're talking basically rural.
Right, bedrock is much more valuable
than the fast that's a fascinating point. That's a very good point.
But we are definitely talking about a שדה not an
עיר. ir. Okay. Now, look beyond, שתיים בשלוש. shtayim beshalosh. Now here's
the basic point about two by forty-nine based on the number of
remaining years. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, ונגרע מערכך, אף מן ההקדש. Venigra
me'erkecha af min hahekdesh.
Now here's something that was not completely clear in the משנה, mishna.
but the גמרא Gemara but the ברייתא makes clear, which is, when
does the redemption take place? Let's say I sanctified it on year
one, and it's been laying around, nobody's redeemed it, הקדש hekdesh hasn't
sold it, and it's now year twenty. Okay, and I want to
redeem it. So the תורה Torah says I redeem it based on
the remaining years. But the remaining years from the time I sanctified
it, or the remaining years from now when I'm redeeming it? Let's
say it's been sitting, you know, not being used in the land
of הקדש, hekdesh, not being sold, not being anything in the land
of הקדש. hekdesh. So on the one hand, you know, the logic
is it should be the remaining years because that its market value
keeps on decreasing based on the upcoming יובל. And that's actually what
we're going to say. You know, you might want to say, well,
let's focus on your original act of הקדש, hekdesh, and at that
time it had a higher market value and that should determine. But
no, we say it's based on its current, you know, the current
reality, and therefore it's based on the remaining years from the time
of redemption. ונגרע מערכך venigra me'erkecha, אף מן ההקדש. af min hahekdesh.
You deduct the years that have passed even if they've passed in
the hands of הקדש, hekdesh, meaning it was already sanctified and it's
just been sitting around in הקדש. hekdesh. שאם אכלה הקדש שנה או
שתים, She'im achla hekdesh shana o shtayim,
if הקדש hekdesh let's say for example maybe הקדש hekdesh has been
making money over the last few years, they've been planting it and
reaping it or, you know, renting it out. We're not going to
worry now about how does that deal with the קדושה, but let's
assume they're able, you know, there's a way they rent it out
and so on, and therefore they're making a profit off of it
over the last few years. אינמי, Inami, or even another scenario, לא
אכלה אלא שהיתה לפניו, lo achla ela shehayta lefanav, it was just
sitting around, הקדש hekdesh got lazy, never did anything with it, and
nobody's been earning any money, and a few years have passed. When
I come to redeem it, is it based on my moment of
הקדש hekdesh or my moment of redemption?
So נותן סלע ופונדיון לשנה, noten sela ufundyon leshana, you still give
a סלע ופונדיון sela ufundyon towards the remaining years. You don't do
it from the beginning and from the time of the הקדש, hekdesh,
which makes a lot of sense because that obviously impacts its current
value and that's when I'm redeeming it is right now. ואם אמר
הריני נותן, Ve'im amar hareni noten, now let's say you say I'd
like please to do an installment plan, and as I said, the
owner has a very high incentive to get this redeemed before the
יובל or it's lost to them completely. So let's say he can't
get the money together. We do not allow an installment plan. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מנין שאם אמרו בעלים be'alim הרינו harenu, נותנים—הרינו,
it's interesting he uses the plural because of בעלים—how be'alim do you
know if the owners say הרינו נותנים כסף כולו כאחד, harenu notnim
kesef kulo ke'echad, הרינו נותנים דבר שנה בשנה, harenu notnim davar shana
beshana,
let's do an installment plan, pay a certain amount per year, שאין
שומעין
להם, she'ein shomin lahem, you don't let them. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
comes and teaches, וחישב לו הכהן את הכסף. vechishev lo hakohen es
hakesef. You figure out the amount, meaning the entire amount, עד כסף
כולו כאחד, ad kesef kulo ke'echad, it has to be the entire
amount. אחד בעלים ואחד כל אדם. Echad be'alim ve'echad kol adam. Now,
whether both an owner and somebody else can redeem it. מה בין
בעלים לכל אדם? Ma bein be'alim lekol adam? What's the difference between
the owner and somebody else? שהבעלים נותנים חומש וכל אדם אינו נותן
חומש. shehabe'alim notnim chomesh vekol adam eino noten chomesh. The בעלים have
to add a חומש, chomesh, together they pay more. Now, of course,
interesting question is, let's say
the
owner and somebody else come at the same time. You know, who
gets first dibs? Presumably the owner because it's in הקדש's hekdesh best
interest and also because you would just think that that's, you know,
being fair and nice to the owner. Let's say somebody else comes
to redeem it.
Let's say somebody the בעלים *ba'alim* and the owner come, and the
בעלים *ba'alim* says I want to redeem it, but it'll take me
a few months to get the money together. The other guy comes
cash in hand, right? Does he have a right to redeem it
right away? You know, let's say even הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* wants to
wait. הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* is interested in waiting because they'll get an
extra fifth, right? So those things are not spelled out, you know,
it just says oh yeah the owner should pay more, but again
I think it's worth thinking about those questions, you know, because both
you would want the system to be biased towards the owner because
you don't want him to lose his field, and because you know
it might be in הקדש *hekdesh*'s best interest, but again not fully
spelled out. Let's take a look now at the next משנה mishna,
*mishnah*. Yes, if somebody else redeems it besides the owner,
then the owner loses it forever?
Yes, and that's what the next משנה mishna *mishnah*'s going to talk
about. So let's read the next משנה *mishnah*. הקדישה וגאלה *hikdishah u'ge'alah*.
Now, let's first read the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* actually. What a thought.
Here's what the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says, okay? It says, ואם גאל
יגאל את השדה המקדיש אתו *ve'im ga'ol yigal et hasadeh hamakdish oto*,
if the one who sanctified it redeems it, ויסף חמישית כסף ערכך
עליו וקם לו *veyasaf chamishit kesef erkecha alav vekam lo*, add a
fifth and gets to keep it, end of story. ואם לא יגאל
את השדה *ve'im lo yigal et hasadeh*, if you didn't do it,
ואם מכר את השדה לאיש אחר *ve'im machar et hasadeh le'ish acher*,
הקדש *hekdesh* sold it to somebody else because they want to get
some money out of this, לא יגאל עוד *lo yiga'el od*, you
are out of the picture. והיה השדה בצאתו ביבל *vehayah hasadeh betzeito
vayovel*, so what happens to the field? קדש להשם כשדה החרם *kodesh
l'Hashem kisdeh hacherem*, it goes over to the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*.
If they sold it to somebody else, you didn't redeem it in
time, then after the יובל *yovel*, they get it. לכהן תהיה אחזתו
*lakohen tihyeh achuzato*. What does it mean they get it? It actually
means that the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* get to divvy it up. Okay,
and we're going to see it's actually a system that's very, you
really want to be in the כהן kohen *kohen* that is on,
that has their cycle, has their weekly service during יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* of the יובל *yovel*. Because at that time when everything reverts,
you would have thought that it would be like divided amongst all
the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim*, but no, it's the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* that
are working then. So man, they got real rich. Anyway, we had
a מחלוקת
*machloket* yesterday, somebody had to pay for it.
Okay,
so we'll talk about that. But wait, I want to say, so
there's two scenarios, and this is what the משנה *mishnah*'s going to
discuss. One scenario is the תורה Torah *Torah* scenario. They sold it
to
somebody. There, if they sold, as soon as they sold it, when
the person paid the money, the קדושה *kedushah* transferred to the money,
the field became de-sanctified and the other person can use it. That's
the תורה *Torah* scenario. In that case, it goes to the כהנים
Kohanim? *kohanim* and there's no issue of paying because it's already been
de-sanctified, it's already not הקדש *hekdesh*. The question that's not discussed in
the תורה *Torah* and discussed in the משנה *mishnah* is, let's say
nobody bought it. What happens when the יובל *yovel* hits? And there,
it remains sanctified. So what's going to happen when the יובל *yovel*
hits and nobody bought it? Will it go to the כהנים Kohanim
*kohanim*? And if it goes to the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*, how do
you remove the sanctity? Because it never got de-sanctified. ואם לא יגאל
ואם מכר
*ve'im lo yigal ve'im machar*.
So the question is, do you read it as one scenario? Right,
you could be that it's two, we'll see that in the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara*.
Can they do it? Are they allowed to work?
Yeah, just כהן *kohen*. I know, so that's the funny thing. They
don't have a נחלה *nachalah* in the sense of, you know, a
part that was given to their שבט Shevet *shevet*, but first of
all they have the area around the ערי הלוים *arei ha'Levi'im*. And
if they, you know, and if they go into business, I don't
know, let's say the
כהן *kohen*, the next Google or Facebook, and then he wants to
invest in an agriculture, you know, there's no prohibition for כהנים Kohanim
*kohanim* to own land and to do agriculture. Although I know, you
read the תורה *Torah* text, not as a נחלה *nachalah*. Right, exactly,
not as a נחלה *nachalah*.
And they could rent it out, they could be landlords. Right, they
can have land and make money off of it, but it's not
as a נחלה *nachalah*. Alright, anyway, let's see the rest of the
משנה *mishnah*. Okay, now, הקדישה וגאלה *hikdishah u'ge'alah*, so if you redeemed
it, אינה יוצאה מידו ביובל *einah yotzah miyado bayovel*. Phew, then you're
safe, then it doesn't go out at יובל *yovel* and you got
your land back. גאלה בנו *ge'alah bno*, let's say your son did
it, יוצאה לאביו ביובל *yotzah l'aviv bayovel*. So then it'll actually go
back to you in the יובל *yovel*. So that's even better, get
somebody else to pay for it and you get it. But that's
a very special case, your son did it.
He would not pay the fifth.
Right, he would not pay the fifth. Right, so in terms of
your idea about having a go-between, your son would be the best
person to do for this.
Is this just in your family?
Just in your family. Yes, yes, we're about to see the next
stage. גאלה אחר או אחד מן הקרובים *ge'alah acher o echad min
hakrovim*, excellent, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks that question, I was waiting
for Rivka for that. גאלה אחר או אחד מן הקרובים *ge'alah acher
o echad min hakrovim*, let's say somebody else, not a relative, or
even a relative who isn't your son, וגאלה מידו *u'ge'alah miyado*, and
even if after that person bought it, you bought it off of
him, so now when the יובל *yovel* hits, not only is it
now in the possession of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, it's in
your possession, but you were not the one to redeem it, יוצאה
לכהנים ביובל *yotzah lakohanim bayovel*, doesn't matter. If you don't redeem it
from the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, even if now somebody else bought
it, you bought it, whatever, it follows the פסוקים *pesukim*, it goes
to the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim*. So if you want to keep that
field in your family, you better redeem it or your son better
redeem it. Now, גאלה אחד מן הכהנים *ge'alah echad min hakohanim*, let's
say one of the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* redeemed it from the בית
המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, והרי היא תחת ידו *ve'harei hi tachat yado*, and
then comes along the יובל *yovel* and it's in his hand. So
the תורה *Torah* says if somebody else, the כהן *kohen* says, somebody
else's hands, it gets, it goes to the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim*. So
now this כהן *kohein* says, hey, let's not bother. לא יאמר *lo
yomar*, don't say, הואיל והיא יוצא לכהנים ביובל והרי היא תחת ידי
הרי היא שלי *ho'il vehia yotzei lakohanim baYovel veharei hi tachat yadi
harei hi sheli*. Look, it's going to go to the כהנים Kohanim
*kohanim* anyway, I'm a כהן *kohein*, I've got it under my possession,
might as well keep it. No, sorry bud.
אלא יוצא מתחת ידו ומתחלקת לכל אחיו הכהנים *ella yotzei mitachat yado
vemit-chalekes lechol echav hakohanim*. No, it's divided equally
point for כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*. Now what's not spelled out explicitly in
this משנה *mishna* is let's say it just is remaining in the
hands of the הקדש *hekdesh*. What, you know, nobody ever redeemed it,
what happens then? That's also not clear in the פסוקים *pesukim*, but
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to turn its attention
to. So let's look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So it's very quickly, so if I'm a non-בעלים *non-ba'alim* and the
כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* like the next day jump on it and then
you know redeem it and then I've lost my chance even just
after one day?
Yes, the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim*, anybody. You know, if you are
a, if you are a land,
presumably this fifty שקל *shekel* for this acreage, again, I'm sure it
depends on the land, but presumably there's a lot of opportunity with
that's below market cost. So, you know, what a smart person who
has some liquid cash would do would be hover around the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, you know, pay somebody to find out if recent
people that have been מקדיש *makdish* their שדה אחוזה *sadeh achuza* and
you know you get a very good deal out of it. You
don't get to keep it because it's only until the יובל *Yovel*
and then it goes to the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*, you know, but
still you get a very good deal out of it. Okay, you
know, the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* have an investment in that happening as
well, the כהנים *kohanim* that are going to get it. Because if
they let the owner redeem it, then they don't get it. If
somebody else gets it, then it's going to go to them.
So a non-בעלים *non-ba'alim* paid the fifty שקל *shekel* if there's less
than two years left?
Presumably, presumably. They wouldn't? No, presumably everybody, the משנה *mishna* says the
only difference is whether about the initial payment is whether you have
the fifth.
But the non-בעלים *non-ba'alim* would have no incentive to buy a field
right within the last two years. That's certainly true, that's certainly true.
Okay. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan, *Tanu rabanan*. אם לא יגאל את השדה
*im lo yiga'al es hasadeh*, if you do not redeem the field,
בעלים *ba'alim*, ואם מכר את השדה *ve'im machar es hasadeh*, and if
it were sold, גזבר *gizbar*, meaning, and so if the field was
not redeemed by the owner, it's just taking פשט *peshat* of the
פסוקים *pesukim*, and the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* sold it to somebody
else, לאיש אחר *le'ish acher*. לאחר ולא לבן *le'acher velo laben*, to
somebody else but not to the son. אתה אומר לאחר ולא לבן
או אינו אלא לאחר ולא לאח *ata omer le'acher velo laben o
eino ela le'acher velo le'ach*?
Maybe it should be the brother? Brother could be a special case
too. Why? Because the concept of the son is a sense of
continuity. It's not really, it's like he did it himself. So the
brother also because the brother by a יבום yibbum, *yibum* case is
considered to be a continuity.
But in our case?
Right. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, כשהוא אומר איש *kshehu omer
ish*, it says if it's bought by a man, so man is
very general. הרי אח אמור *harei ach amur*, so it's even a
brother. הא מני מקיים אחר *ha mani mekayem acher*, so what does
it mean other? You know, it has to be something that's other
than you. Other implies so implies that there's a certain type of
a person that would not be considered other. So ולא לבן *velo
laben*, your son, your son is not other, your son is continuity.
ומה ראית לרבות את הבן ולהוציא את האח et ha'ach, *umah ra'isa
lerabbos es haben ulehotzi es ha'ach*? Okay, so you have to choose
one person that you're going to say has that sense of continuity.
So what makes you say son and not brother? מרבה אני marbeh
ani את הבן שכן קם תחת אביו לייעודה ולעבד עברי *marbeh ani
es haben shekein kam tachas aviv le'iyuda le'eved Ivri*. There are two
other הלכות *halachos* that we know the son is considered a continuity.
One is explicit in the Torah. Like it says in the beginning
of משפטים *Mishpatim*, a man buys whatever a Hebrew slave woman, you
know, אמה עברייה *amah Ivriya*, and it says that he has to,
what's the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? אשר לא יעדה והפדה *asher lo ye'adah
vehefdah*. Okay, so this money that he gives to the father, really
it's you know a Jewish girl and the father is, I mean
this just really speaks to the economic harsh economic realities of the
time, that you know that the father has to you know support
his daughters and daughters were not normally go out and work. So
you want to get them married off. And if you can't get
them married off, then maybe you actually sell them as little slave
girls. I mean that's the story in the beginning of משפטים *Mishpatim*.
So thankfully we're not going to discuss that too much now. When
we get to קידושין *Kiddushin* we can discuss that. Which is discussing
קידושין *Kiddushin*. Anyway, but the Torah says that because it's obviously also
very similar to the scenario where the father marries off his underage
girls, the Torah says that the person who purchased her, you know
it's not full purchase because it's עבד עברי eved ivri *eved Ivri*,
whatever, that engaged in this transaction can turn the money that was
used to do this sort of having her as this slave woman
into כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin *kesef kiddushin*. And that's called ייעוד yi'ud
*yi'ud*. So he can turn it into a קידושין *kiddushin*, which is
probably the best for certainly the father and the girl. But if
he doesn't want to, his son can also have that right. אשר
לא יעדה *asher lo ye'adah*, what does the פסוק *pasuk* say? אשר
לא יעדה והפדה *asher lo ye'adah vehefdah*. No, no, but it says
him or son. It says ואם לבנו ייעדנה *ve'im livno ye'adenah*. Right.
So there you see the son, although the father was the one
that paid the money, the son is considered to be a continuity
of the father. That's one case. ולעבד עברי *ule'eved Ivri*. And עבד
עברי eved ivri? *eved Ivri* is another case because what happens if
a person, again this is a parallel case except with a Jewish
man not a Jewish girl, buys an עבד עברי eved ivri, *eved
Ivri* and he so he works for six years he goes free
in the seventh year. Let's say the master dies. So if the
master dies, the slave goes free. Except if it's the son. Because
again the son is considered to be a continuity of the father
and therefore the slave would not go free. So here are two
cases where it's a continuity. of the father, and therefore we should
focus on the son. So the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה adaraba מרבה
אני את האח, how about the brother?
Since קם תחת אחיו ליבום, kam tachat achiv leyibbum, he does יבום,
yibbum. and that clearly is considered להקים שם אחיו, lehakim shem achiv,
and he inherits, you know, his brother's property and all of that.
So that certainly is considered a continuity of the brother. So then
maybe I should focus on the brother? So the גמרא Gemara, says
no, כלום יש יבום אלא במקום שאין בן. klum yesh yibbum ela
bemakom she'ein ben. The whole point of having to turn to the
brother is because there is no son. So if it's between son
and brother, the son obviously has much more of the sense of
continuity than the brother. The brother is only comes to stand in
when there is no son.
Okay, היש בן, ha'yesh ben, if there is a son, אין יבום.
ein yibbum. There wouldn't be a יבום. yibbum. So son is obviously
has a higher in the hierarchy. So the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק
ליה דהכא תרתי והכא חדא. veteipokei dehacha tarti vehacha chada. Okay, that
was a lovely answer, why couldn't but why didn't you even give
a simpler answer? Two against one, right? ייעוד yi'ud and עבד עברי
eved ivri, against יבום. yibbum So just have given the simple quantitative
answer, although the other answer was obviously more deeply satisfying. But anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says משום דעבד עברי מהאי פירכא נמי הוא דנפקא.
mishum de'eved ivri mehai pircha nami hu denafka. Wait, because how do
we know the הלכה halacha of עבד עברי? The only thing the
תורה is explicit about is the ייעוד yi'ud. הלכה, halacha, right? That
the son can use it, make it into כסף קידושין with this
slave girl. But how do we know the הלכה halacha that the
slave man continues working for the son if the father dies? We
only know it, there's another discussion in another גמרא, and we ask,
we know that one person it's a continuity, and we ask is
it brother, is it son? And the only reason we settle on
son for this הלכה halacha of the slave is because of the
same argument, that the son is more powerful than the brother because
only brother only has status when there is no son. So let
me just finish this thought. מהאי פירכא נמי הוא דנפקא, mehai pircha
nami hu denafka, we only know that הלכה halacha from the same
argument. כלום יש יבום אלא במקום שאין בן, klum yesh yibbum ela
bemakom she'ein ben, that the only status of a brother is when
there is no son. So yes, it's two against one, but the
reason it's two against one is ultimately it rests on this logic
that the son has greater status in the sense of continuity than
the father. So if we're going to say that one person then
the brother, right. So if we're going to say that there's one
person who can redeem and it's not considered an other, somebody who
is else, who's other, then that one person we're going to focus
on will be the son. Now it is an interesting question about
whether the son would pay a חומש. chomesh. It doesn't say so
in the משנה, and again I'll see if there's some discussion about
that, but if so, then that's a nice way to do a
little work around to get it back to you and to have
this without paying the חומש.
chomesh. So it's at least an interesting question in terms of a
daughter, because on the one hand you wouldn't do יבום yibbum if
it's a daughter, right? On the other hand, she you know she
can't do ייעוד. yi'ud And then but then what about the wife?
Okay, very per... what does it, does you know אשה כגופו?
isha kegufu?
Thank you. So you've now written the rest of the גמרא till
the משנה, so let's keep on reading. Okay, so the גמרא says
like this, yes, that's
my question about the then the the temple is letting the family
keep the field without charging the extra.
Right, that seems to be the case. Well, it's not their choice,
it's what the תורה says. The תורה only says a חומש chomesh
if it's the person himself.
You know, so if it's so but this is a little bit
of a loophole. He will get it back. But again, if you
go to sort of the סברא svara I was trying to give
about the purpose of a חומש, chomesh, you know, if I buy
it back myself, it does undermine a little bit the power of
that initial act. If my son buys it back and I'm only
going to get it back into my possession in 20, 30 years,
my initial act still retains a lot of that initial power. So
I would see that the real reason of the חומש, chomesh, even
if it prevents it from being lost to me and that's what
I benefited by being my son, it still, you know, the חומש
chomesh is really particularly because of my initial act of הקדש. That's
how I would understand it. Okay, let's keep continuing growing. We are
definitely going to get to the משנה by the end of today.
So it says like this, so
the גמרא says like this, בעי רבא בר אבוה. ba'ei Rava bar
Avuha. So רבא בר אבוה Rava bar Avuha asked, זו בת מהו
שתעמיד שדה לאביה? zu bat mahu sheta'amid sadeh la'aviha? Let's say the
daughter buys the field back. Will it get preserved and then at
the יובל go back to the father? כיון דלענין יבום בן ובת
כי הדדי פטרי, keivan delinyan yibbum ben ubat kiyadadi patrei,
so since regarding יבום yibbum, a son and daughter are the same
and they exempt from יבום, meaning it's considered to be that the
father's, you know, sort of memory is preserved, that there's a continuity
regardless of son or daughter, so מוקמה, mukma, so therefore it will
stay in the father's possession if she buys it back, that's considered
a continuity. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say, כיון דלענין
נחלה, keivan delinyan nachalah, when it comes to inheritance, בת במקום בן
כאחר דמיא, bat bemakom ben ke'acher damya, a daughter is considered other
when it comes to sons, she's lower in the hierarchy unless there's
no sons. But if there are sons, she's lower in the hierarchy.
So therefore,
where are we? I lost my place.
So לא מוקמה, lo mukma, she doesn't, right? And the point here
could be, so on the one hand you're right, you could raise
the question maybe it shouldn't matter whether there are sons or aren't
sons, if she's doing the redeeming. But the point is that again,
how much conceptually is there an idea of the same sort of
legal concept of continuity? And you're exactly right. You could ask the
question by עבד עברי, you can ask the question by אמה עבריה
amah ivriyah because the girl can't do ייעוד to a woman, but
you could ask the question by עבד עברי, what would be the
הלכה halacha as well? Is there that sense of continuity? And the
idea of inheritance is a fascinating one because on the one hand
the daughter inherits, and on the other hand it's only when there's
no son, and what happens to the inheritance? She marries somebody from
outside the שבט and from or even outside the family, and then
that sense of that being remaining part of the family ancestral lands,
it gets diverted, right, once she marries out. So in this sort
of patriarchal structure, in which sort of things are defined by father,
son,
and so on, when the idea of how does the daughter fit
in as being seen as continuity or not within that type of
a structure is more of a question. So that's the גמרא's issue.
So let's see what the גמרא's answer is. תא שמע Ta shema
come and
hear here. דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Detana devei Rabbi Yishmael כל שהוא
אחר במקום בן. Kol shehu acher bimkom ben. Anybody that's considered other
vis-a-vis the son. Anybody that in any case would have a lower
status than the son. והא נמי במקום בן כי אחר דמיא Veha
nami bimkom ben ke'acher damya that presumably includes the daughter, because the
daughter does have, although she has some aspects of continuity, she's lower
on the hierarchy than the son, and it's only the son and
nobody else. So that is the conclusion of the גמרא, and again,
it does really just reflect the larger structural system here about the
nature of this type of patriarchal system where families are defined by
the men and not by the women, the family structures. So, that
was daughter. Now,
בעי רמי בר חמא Ba'ei Rami bar Chama
אישה מי ממי לה שדה בעל? Isha mi mami la sadeh ba'al?
בעל מוקים לה שכן ירשה Ba'al mukim lah sheken yarsha. הוא. If
the woman sold the- was מקדיש a field, would there be somebody
that would play the role of a son? Who would play the
role of a son if a woman was מקדיש the field? There's
two candidates: the son or the husband.
On the one hand, they both can inherit her. Who inherits if
the husband is alive and she's still married to him? The husband
inherits. If she's divorced or the husband is dead, her son inherits.
So because the husband inherits first, you might think that that means
that the husband represents that continuity, but there's a way that the
inheritance of the son is more powerful. How is that? Let's take
a look. So who is מוקים לה, mukim lah, who keeps the
field in her property?
בעל מוקים לה Ba'al mukim lah שכן ירשה. Is it the husband
because he inherits her and inherits her first? או דילמא בן מוקים
לה, O dilma ben mukim lah, or maybe the son does it?
שכן נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק. Sheken notel barauy kevemuchzak. Let's say she dies,
there's no husband- the husband divorced her or is dead, and then
after she's dead, her father dies. Does that inheritance pass on to
her son, assuming whatever she doesn't have brothers? So when it's an
inheritance that goes to her son, the son gets stuff. The son
gets stuff that even wasn't in her possession when she died, that
comes in later. Debts that were collected, other inheritance, all of that
will pass down to the son when the son inherits. When her
husband inherits her, he only inherits things that were in her possession
when she died.
This was the debt.
This was the debt. So then her brothers or whatever, it would
go by her biological family.
Or her son. Anyway, so therefore on the one hand the husband
comes first, and on the other hand the son's inheritance is more
powerful. There's a greater sense of continuity. And you could sort of
say that conceptually, when she dies it's like it transfers to the
husband if there's a husband, but when there's a son and it's
passed on to the son, it's like the son is a continuity.
One is more of a sense of transfer, the other is a
sense of continuity. So that's the גמרא's question. Let's see the answer.
So the גמרא says, תיקו. Teiku. Okay, so that was the answer.
Good question, we don't know.
Now, the answer what happens if the wife redeems it for the
husband?
That would be אחר במקום בן acher bimkom ben because a wife
doesn't inherit from the husband and whatever
that- even though אשתו כגופו ishto kegufu
and whatever, still, yeah, but that sense of continuity is only focused
on the son. Okay. בעי מיניה רמי בר חמא, Ba'ei mineih Rami
bar Chama, oh, we only have one minute.
מרב חסדא meRav Chisda הקדישה פחות משתי שנים לפני היובל hikdisha pachot
mishtei shanim lifnei haYovel מהו שתצא לכהנים? mahu shetetzei laKohanim? Let's say
he sanctified it less than two years. So we now know you
pay full freight. Will that have an impact also in terms of
whether it can be- who gets it? If you redeemed it within
two years and you redeemed it yourself for fifty שקל, maybe it
should still go to the כהנים. Why would you say such a
bizarre thing? אמר ליה מאי דעתך? Amar leih mai da'atach? He says,
what are you thinking? ונגרע מערכך Venigra me'erkecha because the פסוק says
you deduct the amount based on the remaining years, and then it
says והיה השדה בצאתו ביובל Vehayah hasadeh betzeito baYovel and then if
it's the יובל it
goes to the כהנים. So you would think דבת גירעון היא, debat
girayon hi, only something that can be deducted maybe goes to the
כהנים. דלאו בת גירעון לא. Delav bat girayon lo.
I'm sorry, you didn't redeem it, I misphrased the question. The question
is you did the full amount before the יובל- you were מקדיש
it within two years before the יובל and you didn't redeem it.
So he thinks maybe it won't go to the כהנים. Why wouldn't
it go to the כהנים? Because the פסוק juxtaposes going to the
כהנים with deducting. So maybe the only thing that goes to the
כהנים is something that would be possible to do a whole deduction
by. This, where it's not possible to do a deduction, you did
it within two years, maybe it wouldn't go to the כהנים even
if you didn't redeem it. So he says no,
אדרבה, aderaba, nope. אם לא יגאל השדה והיה השדה בצאתו ביובל. Im
lo yiga'al hasadeh vehayah hasadeh betzeito baYovel. The other פסוק says if
you don't redeem it, then it goes to the כהנים. So really
it's not based on the ability to do a deduction, it's based
on the ability to redeem. והאי נמי בת גאולה היא, v'hai nami
bat geula hi, any field that can be redeemed goes, if it's
not redeemed, goes to the כהנים. So even within two years, although
there's no deduction, because it can be redeemed, it does go to
the כהנים. Let's just finish up to the משנה. גאל אחד מן
הכהנים, ga'al echad min hakohanim, one of the כהנים redeemed it and
he says, you know what, don't bother, I'll keep it. Very generous
of him. Okay, so תנו רבנן, so we taught, לכהן תהיה אחוזתו.
lakohen tihye achuzato. מה תלמוד לומר, ma talmud lomar, what does it
mean that the כהן gets this as an inheritance if it, if
the owners don't redeem it? מניין לשדה שיוצא לכהנים ביובל וגאל אחד
מן הכהנים, minayin l'sadeh sheyotzei lakohanim bayovel v'ga'al echad min hakohanim, how
do you know that this field that was redeemed, וגאל אחד, v'ga'al
echad, that was sanctified, וגאל אחד מן הכהנים, v'ga'al echad min hakohanim,
one of the כהנים redeemed it himself? מניין שלא יאמר הואיל ויוצא
לכהנים הרי היא תחת ידי ותהא שלי? minayin shelo yomar ho'il v'yotzei
lakohanim harei hi tachat yadi v'tehei sheli? He says, look, כהנים are
going to get it anyway, now it's in my possession, I might
as well keep it. ודין הוא, v'din hu, and it makes sense.
בשל אחרים אני זוכה, b'shel acherim ani zoche, if I would get
a portion in a field that was being possessed by somebody else
completely, בשל עצמי לא כל שכן, b'shel atzmi lo kol shekein, how
much more so that I am now right now in possession of
this? So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the verse says, אחוזתו. achuzato. No,
it has to be like your inheritance. אחוזה שלו ואין זו שלו.
achuza shelo v'ein zo shelo. If you want something to be yours,
then it means only your inheritance is yours. Something that basically is
not yours, you don't have special dibs to it. Okay, this wasn't
your inheritance, this was something you bought from somebody else, you don't
have any special rights. הא כיצד, ha keitzad, so what do you
do? יוצא מתחת ידו ומתחלקת לכל הכהנים, yotzei mitachat yado umitchaleket l'chol
hakohanim, that it gets, he takes it out, it's divided equally by
the כהנים. Not all the כהנים, as we'll see, but it gets
divided equally. The one case we have not discussed, which is the
next משנה, is the case of, so now we know if the
owner redeems it, he keeps it. If somebody else redeems it, it
gets desanctified and then it goes to the כהנים. What if nobody
redeems it and it was in the hand of הקדש and it
was still sanctified? What happens then? That will be the משנה we'll
see tomorrow.